Finding Aid for the Nat Segaloff Papers PASC.0354
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nat Segaloff papers
1958-2008
UCLA Library Special Collections
Segaloff, Nat 1948-
PASC.0354
41.5 Linear Feet (83 boxes)
14 Born-digital Carriers (14 optical discs)
The collection consists of materials pertaining to Nat Segaloff's career as a freelance writer, producer, teacher and journalist. A highlight of this collection is the large amount of material pertaining to the Hollywood blacklist.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
The collection is a gift of the creator, Nat Segaloff.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9967092913606533
Biographical Note
Nat Segaloff is a freelance writer, producer, teacher and journalist whose broadcast, writing and hosting career has included positions for CBS radio, Westinghouse Television, network affiliates and independents, and U.S. field producer for the BBC. He has written special material for Edward Asner, William Baldwin, Angela Bassett, Warren Beatty, Maria Bello, Annette Bening, Toni Braxton, Jamie Lee Curtis, Dom DeLuise, Michael Douglas, Michael J. Fox, LisaGay Hamilton, Herbie Hancock, Dustin Hoffman, Anjelica Huston, Samuel L. Jackson, Natalie Maines, Esai Morales, Sarah Jessica Parker, Paula Poundstone, Alan Rosenberg, James Whitmore and numerous other celebrities and public figures. Segaloff's writing has appeared in Film comment, International documentary, Boston magazine, Written by, Boston after dark, Time out (USA), The Journal of the Producers Guild of America, The Word Guild magazine, Audio/video interiors, The Tab, Animation magazine, American movie classics magazine, Moving pictures, The Boston globe and The Christian Science Monitor. He has taught on the faculty of Boston University and Boston College, and worked on motion picture advertising and publicity campaigns for Paramount, Disney, Columbia, United Artists, Fox, and MGM. In addition, he has written books on personalities such as: John Huston, Arthur Penn, Stirling Silliphant, and William Friedkin, and on such topics as: the Hollywood Blacklist, employment in the television field, romantic films, etiquette, and writing for television.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials pertaining to Segaloff's career as freelance writer, producer, teacher and journalist. A highlight of the collection is the extensive collection of Hollywood Blacklist materials collected and used by Segaloff as research material. Included are materials related to Segaloff's newspaper, magazine, radio, television and film projects. Amongst these projects are "Alien Voices." In 1996 Nat, John de Lancie, and Leonard Nimoy formed a production company named Alien Voices to produce audiobook dramatizations of classic science fiction stories acted by "Star Trek" performers. The idea came from John's recreated production of the Orson Welles classic Invasion From Mars that was done for LA Theatre Works and NPR. Because the radio play was so short, Nat and John wrote a sequel, When Welles Collide, that trashed tabloid news media. They had so much fun that they formed a company to keep doing it. They did five titles for Simon & Schuster Audio. Included in the collection are marked-up copies of the scripts, sample tapes, never-released behind-the-scenes footage (DVD, VHS and mini cassette), audio outtakes, and corporate paperwork.
Another project of note is the Segaloff radio play, "The Waldorf Conference." "The Waldorf Conference" is a play about the secret meeting held in New York's Waldorf-Astoria Hotel on November 24 and 25, 1947 among 48 film company businessmen to decide how the industry should react to the HUAC hearings just concluded in Washington from October 20-30 at which charges were leveled against 10 men for alleged Communist party membership.
Segaloff compiled a detailed description of the collection contents which is attached to the finding aid as a PDF.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Projects
Series 2. Hollywood Blacklist
Series 3. Research Material, 1970-
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Projects
Series 2. Hollywood Blacklist
Series 3. Research Material, 1970-
- Projects, Series 1.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes contracts, story files, supporting documentation and script drafts. Most of the titles have been produced.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - A & E Biography Projects (Box 64)
    Segaloff project clippings -- Stan Lee: The ComiX-Man.
    General note
    See Segaloff annotations for Box 8 for contents information.
  - A & E Biography Projects, papers; AV materials; PEZ dispenser (Box 65)
    Stan Lee: The ComiX-Man: notes, permissions, research materials, PEZ dispenser -- Marvel Prologues. (Buena Vista Home Video International)
  - Alien Voices (Box 69)
    Complete audiobook collection -- Invasion from Mars (LA Theatre Works) -- First Men in the Moon (VHS) -- DVD set (home video of Alien Voices events) -- CD set (rehearsals).
    See Segaloff annotation Box 6 for contents information.
    Includes 6 DVDs and 18 CDs.
  - Alien Voices (Box 76)
    Press kit -- Management files -- First Men in the Moon (live broadcast).
  - Alien Voices, papers (Box 77)
    Leonard (Nimoy) and John (de Lancie) articles -- www.alienvoices.com - website registration papers -- Alien Voices (paperwork) -- Photos (behind the scenes photographs) -- The Lost World (audio book paperwork).
  - Alien Voices: Produced and Unproduced Scripts (Box 27)
    Mysterious Island -- Lost Horizon -- Invasion from Mars/When Welles Collide -- The Lost World -- Journey to the Center of the Earth -- The Invisible Man -- The First Men in the Moon (audio and TV) -- Alien Voices promotional program.
    In 1996 Nat, John de Lancie, and Leonard Nimoy formed a production company named Alien Voices to produce audiobook dramatizations of classic science fiction stories acted by "Star Trek" performers. They did five titles for Simon & Schuster Audio. These boxes contain Nat's marked-up copies of the scripts, sample tapes, never-released behind-the-scenes footage, audio outtakes, and corporate paperwork. Also includes some photographs of radio performances, programs, correspondence, and notes.
  - Arthur Penn: American Director (University Press of Kentucky), 2011 (Box 82)
    manuscript and addenda
    1 CD.
  - Assorted Film Projects, AV materials (Box 51)
    Healing the Hate -- Laughing Till It Hurt -- Moon and Teeth -- The Brink's Job -- Extravaganza -- Dazzle: The Entertainment Magazine -- The Baxters.
    See Segaloff annotations Box 18 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects (Box 4)
    Titles include: Nicolas -- Newspaper Picture -- North Hollywood High Class of '61 -- Parole Board -- Reality Binge -- Rock n Roll Moments -- Dodi and the Devil -- Films of Alan Smithee -- Hand That Rocks the Camera -- Incredible Shrinking Candy Bar -- IXG (Innocent by Guilt) -- Law and Order -- Robert Lees (blacklisted screenwriter) Documentary.
    See Segaloff annotations Box 19 for descriptions/history of each project. Includes scripts, contracts, correspondence, and other related paperwork.
  - Assorted Projects (Box 44)
    Devil's Run -- Fait Accompli -- Stan Lee: The Comix Man -- Larry King: Talk of Fame -- Darryl F. Zanuck -- John Belushi: Funny You Should Ask -- Evening Magazine -- P.M. Magazine -- Day's End -- The Woman in Red (Gene Wilder, Gilda Radner Interviews) -- Iron Man: the Fantastic Four Spider Man Prologues -- Gregory Mcdonald Interview -- TV (WSBK) 38 -- Movie Loft & Co. -- New England's Greatest Entertainers -- Inside the Giant Ocean Tank -- Ask the Manager -- Segaloff Demo Reel -- Pre-Occupations -- Stephen King Interview -- Back in the World -- New England Today -- Daytime -- Dan Kimmel Roast -- KNBC News (Nat) -- Hurricane Billy discussed with Nat -- Robert Altman Interview (Streamers) -- Big Bad John (Milius) (Red Dawn Interview).
    See Segaloff annotations Box 8 for contents information.
    Includes 2 DVDs.
  - Assorted Projects, AV materials (Box 46)
    Shari Lewis (A & E Biography) -- Douglas Trumbull Interview (Brainstorm) -- Joel and Ethan Coen Interview (Blood Simple) -- John Schlesinger Interview (The Falcon and the Snowman) -- Segaloff Resume Presentation Reel -- Laughing Till It Hurt -- The Baxters -- Chickens -- Big Shots' Starting Shots -- Fun With Dick and Perry -- Dazzle (pilot) -- Rock and Roll Moments.
    See Segaloff annotations for Box 11 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 50)
    Civil Liberties Christmas Carols -- Close -- Glenn Close Interview (Maxie) -- Comic Book Collectors -- Paul Crump -- Angry Man -- Audiobooks Today/Audiobook Cafe.
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 14 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 52)
    Blacklisting Then and Now -- Day's End -- Facts on File Foreword -- Gladys (Malcolm Leo) -- Hate (full title: Healing the Hate).
    See Segaloff annotations Box 18 for descriptions/history of each project.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 53)
    Boston Herald Interviews -- Hollywood Fights Back...Again.
    Folder titles. See Segalof annotations Box 18 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 54)
    Hollywood Moments -- Boston/ACLU of Massachusetts/Emerson (blacklist seminar) -- Jacob's Pillow -- Legal Briefs ACLU Mass -- Malcolm Leo Q & A -- Banned Books. (ACLU of Southern California)
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 18 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 55)
    Brats (screenplay) -- Moguls and the Mob(Treatment and research) -- Murrow -- Palmer Raids -- Paul Mazursky's America -- Predator (Jack Olsen book).
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 20 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 56)
    Screen Saver (Segaloff memoir) -- Sound of the Cities -- Stax Records -- That's Tantamount.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 57)
    That's Tantamount -- Underthrow the Government -- When Clowns Attack.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 66)
    Marvel Prologues fiscal files -- Buena Vista Home Video International paperwork -- John Belushi: Funny You Should Ask (scripts, drafts, budgets) -- Larry King: Talk of Fame (scripts, notes, research).
  - Assorted Projects, papers; vhs (Box 67)
    Fait Accompli (independent short film papers and VHS) -- DFZ/File -- Darryl F. Zanuck (A & E Biography project) -- Shari Lewis & Lamb Chop (script, research, budgets, etc.).
    Folder titles. See Segalof annotations Box 8 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 70)
    Laughing Till It Hurt (documentary on Charles Chaplin's Tramp character) -- Laurel and Hardy TV Show -- Locations -- Losing Interest -- Lovelace, Linda (interview) -- Maltin, Leonard -- McLaughlin, Richard E. -- Media (radio drama) -- Meet the Newlyweds (radio drama) -- Mentioned in Passing -- Mimieux, Yvette ("The Black Hole") -- Movie Madness Bookstore -- Movie Merchandising -- Movie Theatre Survival Game -- Music Hall Closing (Sack Music Hall) -- My Mother the Gangster (story treatment) -- Naked (story notes) -- Nichols, Mike (book proposal).
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 11 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 71)
    Oed! (radio musical) -- Of This Time, Of That Place (student film) -- Olmos, Edward James (interview) -- "People Who Stood Up Oscar" (Moving Pictures Magazine 11-06) -- PM Magazine (television program) -- Pair Probes Pix Pan --Partisans of Vilna (interview with Aviva Kempner) -- Peltier, Ed (script) -- Perry, Frank -- Pigeons (article) -- Press Agent (newspaper feature) -- Press Agent Confessing -- Projectionist, Boston's Oldest (article) -- Reader's Digest (magazine review) -- Reeler-Dealers, The:Time Out -- Reviews -- Ritt, Martin -- Rolling Boulder -- Russell, Craig.
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 16 for content information.
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 72)
    Saturday Matinees (newspaper article) -- Saturday Night Fever -- Screen Seen -- Short, Marjie (Kudzu) -- Something Wild (interviews with Jeff Daniels, Ray Liotta, Jonathan Demme) -- Subways (magazine article) -- Starsky and Hutch of the VA (Herald Magazine) -- Stix Nix Flix -- Summerthing -- "Tab" stories (newspaper) -- Teen Fan Mags -- Theatre Etiquette -- Time Out -- To Bee or Not to Bee -- Toast to Lenny Bruce --Tough Guys (interviews with Burt Lancaster; Kirk Douglas; Dana Carvey and Eli Wallach) -- Trends in Film (Boston Magazine) -- Turkey House on Cape Cod (Herald Magazine) -- TV Movie Cutting (Boston Herald Magazine).
  - Assorted Projects, papers (Box 73)
    Videotape Piracy (newspaper article) -- Vinton, Will -- WBUR Fundraising Package 1980 -- Weather Lady (newspaper feature) -- WEEI-FM (sample scripts) -- Wexler, Haskell (interview) -- Wexler, Norman (interview) -- Whitlock, Albert (interview) -- Wild in the Cellar -- Wilder, Gene and Dom DeLuise (newspaper interview) -- Xerox Copy Story (newspaper article) -- York, Susannah (feature).
  - Assorted Titles (Box 37)
    Dazzle; Dealing; Denouement; Dergarabedian, Paul; The Real Paper; Drizzle; Dukakis, Olympia; Egleson, Jan; Evening Magazine; Evening: Used Film Tips
    Folder titles. See Box 15 annotations for contents information.
  - Assorted Titles (Box 38)
    Evening (cont.); Fifty Reasons To Fail; Film Industry Game; Filmgoer's Bill of Rights; Emmys; Film Row; Fish Tales
    Folder titles. See Box 15 in annotated content list for contents.
  - Assorted Titles (Box 39)
    Flick You; Flush with the Devil; Freed, Justin; Friends of Eddie Coyle; Getting Bent; Fremer, Michael; Ghost Story; Gleason, Jackie; Graves, Peter; Great Film School Hoax; Great Patriotic Moments in American History; Grodin, Charles; Greatest Press Agent in the World; GYRO TV; Hamlin, Sonya; Hanff, Helene; Hanging In, Hanging Out; Harris, Linda; Hawmps Presskit; Hazzard, Peter.
    Folder titles. See Box 15 annotated content list for contents.
  - Assorted Titles (Box 40)
    Absence of Malice (Paul Newman Interview) -- Marjory Adams Interview -- Against the Law -- Air Show Interviews -- Hollywood on the Charles -- Hollywood Party -- Hollywood: What Made Hollywood -- How to Peddle Your Picture -- Humor Magazines -- Sam Jaffe -- Journal of the Producers Guild of America -- Kauycheck, Tom -- Kid Slang: Word Guild -- Kidvid -- Stephen King -- Jack Larson.
    Folder titles. See Box 14 and 15 annotations for contents information.
  - Assorted Titles (Box 46)
    Jane Alexander Intro. -- Robert Altman -- Am I Normal -- And For the Straights, the Documentary -- Annie -- Art Film Business in Boston -- Attack of the Sequel Monsters -- Frank Avruch TV Special -- The Baxters.
    Folder titles. See Segaloff Box 14 annotations for contents information.
  - Assorted Titles (Box 47)
    Baxters -- Bean Streets -- Warren Beatty Book -- Billy in the Lowlands -- Blackside Films -- Blind Bidding Bill -- Blue Lagoon -- Boston College Guide -- Boston's Best-Looking People -- Boston Underground Newspaper stories -- Boston Filmmakers.
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 14 for contents information.
  - Backstory and other Segaloff Monographs (Box 58)
    Code Blue -- Mr. Huston/Mr. North -- John Milius interviews (CD).
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations Box 3 for content information.
    Includes 1 CD.
  - Backstory and other Segaloff Monographs, papers (Box 60)
    Mr. Huston/Mr. North manuscript -- John Milius interviews -- Paul Mazursky interviews.
  - Backstory and other Segaloff Monographs, papers (Box 63)
    Stirling Silliphant manuscript -- Walon Green manuscript -- Paul Mazursky interview.
    Folder titles. See Segaloff annotations for Box 3 content information.
  - Backstory and other Segaloff Monographs, papers (Box 64)
    Paul Mazursky interview
    See Segaloff annotations Box 3 for content information.
  - Backstory and other Segaloff Monographs, audio cassettes (Box 64)
  - Blackballing (Box 82)
    Segaloff Boston Herald article.
    Restricted until after the death of Nat Segaloff and A. Alan Friedberg.
  - Darryl F. Zanuck: Twentieth Century Filmmaker, 3/4" video cassette (Box 43)
    courtesy copy of Nat''s A & E Biography.
  - Director's Cuts (Box 82)
    unpublished article for Film Comment.
  - Gene Hackman Interview, 1999 September 22 (Box 44)
    1 Digital Betacam cassette. PAL format.
  - John Belushi A & E Biography (box 1 of 2), beta SP tapes (Box 61)
    Segaloff wrote and produced the A & E "Biography" on John Belushi with the permission and cooperation of the late comic actor's widow Judy and brother Jim. The show consisted entirely of clips from these two boxes of tapes that Judy shot with John's friends shortly after his death, before the memories faded. Judy has the original tapes. These are BetaSP dubs that Segaloff made for the show.
    Inventory in box 1.
  - John Belushi A & E Biography (box 2 of 2), beta SP tapes (Box 62)
    Inventory in box 1. Tapes care of UCLA Film and Television Archive.
  - John Belushi Project, 6 audio cassettes (Box 69)
    See Segaloff annotations Box 5 for contents information.
  - John Belushi: Funny You Should Ask, 1994; beta SP tapes (Box 41)
    Footage originally shot for MTV's "John Belushi: Rock n' Roll Actor."
    Property of Judith Belushi. For reference only. Inventory in box.Continued in box 42.
  - John Belushi: Funny You Should Ask, 1994; beta SP tapes (Box 42)
  - Kent State Radio Documentary 10th Anniversary (1980), 7 " open reel audio tape (Box 5)
    Segaloff project for WEEI-FM (CBS).
  - Movie Loft & Company, 3/4" video cassette (Box 43)
    The nightly movie series on WSBK-TV in Boston was "Movie Loft" hosted by Dana Hersey. If the movie ran short, "Movie Loft & Company" produced filler, mostly press junket pieces, but often just essays. Nat hosted and produced many of these interstitials.
  - Mr. North Monograph Coverage, clippings (Box 59)
  - Orson Welles Complex, 2 10" open reel analog tapes (Box 5)
    Interviews and show master tape.
    Broadcast on WITS AM, Boston.
  - Sack Theaters Article (Box 82)
  - Segaloff Films, film (Box 68)
    "Chickens!" color negative and optical track -- "Chickens!" unidentified rolls (2) -- "Dealing" B & W dupe neg and optical track -- "Dealing" B & W composite release print -- "Moon & Teeth" color reversal A & B roll and optical track -- "Extravaganza!" Color reversal A, B, and C roll and optical track -- "Extravaganza!" reference DVD -- 16mm snippet of Peter Bogdanovich and Cybill Shepard, and of Alan Friedberg (Sack Theatres).
    Student and professional short subjects. See Segaloff annotations Box 14 for contents information.
  - Segaloff Films, film (Box 69)
    Hawmps!" long featurette color reversal and color positive release prints -- "Hawmps!" short featurette color reversal print -- "Dealing" B & W original reversal, mixing elements, and mag mix -- "Chickens" color positive composite release print -- John Belushi: Funny You Should Ask --
    Student and professional short subjects. See Segaloff annotations for contents information.
  - Segaloff/McClintick/Brudnoy Interview, 1982 August 3; 7 " open reel audio tape (Box 5)
    Aircheck of a three-way interview on WBZ-AM radio in Boston between host David Brudnoy and author David McClintick who had just published the book "Indecent Exposure" abut David Begelman's embezzlement at Columbia Pictures. Segaloff gave David McClintick some tips about the movie business in the course of his writing the book and David Begelman had me on the show to contribute. Also on the tape: interview with Liane Brandon 8/82. Brandon is the independent social issue filmmaker if New Day Films.
  - Stan Lee Biography Project Storyboards and Notes (Box 82)
  - Stan Lee Biography Research Notes, 1996 (Box 49)
    Loose leaf binders with transcripts of the interviews plus show "Bible" including copies of signed releases, film clip licenses, budgets, etc.
- Hollywood Blacklist, Series 2.
  Item descriptions by Nat Segaloff.
  - Ephemera, Subseries 1.
    - Assorted Titles (Box 48)
      Brandon, Liane -- Brown, Ken -- Burns, Kevin -- Cain, Jess -- Charles River Academy -- Chickens!
      Folder titles. See Segaloff Box 9 annotations for contents information.
    - Blacklisted, 1995 September (Box 3)
      Article in KCRW's monthly newsletter by Tony Kahn.
      See Segaloff Box 9 annotations for contents information.
    - Blacklisted Newsletter, 1995 February (Box 3)
    - Blacklisted: The Man Behind the Door, 1994 (Box 1)
      Tony Kahn's radio drama about growing up with the fear that J. Edgar Hoover was going to come for him because his father, Gordon Kahn, was blacklisted (q.v. audiocassettes of the broadcast show in Box 10)
      A National Radio drama on the Hollywood Blacklist.See Segaloff Box 9 annotations for contents information.
    - Communist Infiltration of Hollywood Motion Picture Industry, 1951 (Box 2)
      Scope and Content
      Hearing transcripts
    - Film Culture Magazine #50-51 (Box 1)
      The famous academic journal which, this issue, published Congressional notice of who testified against whom at HUAC's 1951 hearings.
    - Film in the Battle of Ideas (Box 2)
      John Howard Lawson's influential paperback signed and inscribed by Lawson.
    - For Justice and Peace (Box 1)
      U.S. Supreme Court brief (actually, a plea) by the Wives of the Hollywood Ten, sold as fundraising item
      By the wives of the Hollywood Ten.
    - Hello Over Hollywood: The Truth About the Movies (Box 2)
      Pamphlet by Dan Gilbert.
    - Hollywood and the First Amendment, 1992 (Box 3)
      In: Constitution, Vol. 4, no. 3
    - Hollywood Fights Back Again, 2007 (Box 3)
      recreation of the famed 1947 anti-HUAC broadcast "Hollywood Fights Back" in which dozens of high-profile entertainers chastised HUAC for infringing on the First Amendment. The original script was written by Norman Corwin, Millard Lampell, and Robert Presnell, Jr. (actress Marsha Hunt's husband). Marsha got permission from Norman for me to adapt it with updated material following 9/11 and we performed it on Friday, October 26, 2007 at the Skirball Cultural Center as an event of the ACLU of Southern California.
    - Hollywood on Trial, 1976 (Box 2)
      Press materials for 1976 documentary about the Hollywood Ten. Written by Arnie Reisman (co-writer of the play "The Waldorf Conference"). Oscar nominated.
    - Hollywood Reds are On the Run (Box 2)
      Pamphlet by Myron C. Fagan.
    - Homeland Conspiracy, 2003 November (Box 3)
      Segaloff article in the WGA journal, "Written By."
    - Kazan Krapfest (Box 1)
      Title assigned by Segaloff: When HUAC informer Elia Kazan was given a Life Achievement Oscar by AMPAS, the shit hit the fan. These are print-outs of some of the commentary surrounding it.
    - Lees-Rinaldo Doc ("The Treasurer's Report") (Box 2)
      AMPAS asked Segaloff to narrate the Academy Film Archives' reconstruction of a 16mm silent home movie by blacklisted writers Robert Lees and Fred Rinaldo for the League of American Writers. This is the paperwork and a video transfer at two speeds, 24 and 18 fps.
      Includes 1 DVD.